WILLIAM KIRKPATRICK READE

Software Development Engineer

williamreade623@Outlook.com

**** +1 256 410 9329

9 GALLATIN, TN

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Skilled Software Development Engineer with over 10 years of experience. Skilled in front-end and back-end development, and distributed systems. Successfully completed numerous projects using different technologies, mostly React.js, Redux, Angular, Next.js, and RxJs for front-end, and Laravel, Cognitor and CakePHP for back-end. Works with different databases like MongoDB, AWS DynamoDB, MySQL, and PostgreSQL. Besides, has solid experience in OOPs like PHP, Python, C#, C++, and Java. Moreover, experienced in solving algorithm problems. Always follows modern development methodologies, including scrum methodology. Acts both as a communicative strong team player and an independent team member who enables processes, investigates, and provides solutions for various tasks. Improves the performance of the team. Good communication and collaborative skills. As a team lead has experience in reviewing team members' code and collaborating with project managers and customers to ensure the successful delivery of projects.

TECHNOLOGY SUMMARY

Languages: JavaScript, TypeScript, PHP, C#, Python, Java, C++

Technologies and React.js, Angular, Next.js, Redux, NgRx, RxJs, Laravel, Cognitor, CakePHP, GraphQL,

Frameworks: SCSS, Tailwind CSS, Bootstrap

DBMS: MySQL, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, AWS DynamoDB

IDEs and Tools: PHPStorm, Visual Studio Code, Docker, Apollo, CyPress, Jest, Jasmin, Karma, Git Bash

Other skills: AWS Cloud Services, Problem Solving, Full Stack Development, Critical Thinking,

Algorithm Design, Team-Oriented, SOLID, Agile (Scrum)

KEY TECHNICAL SKILLS

Front-end development

- Front-end development using React.js, Next.js, Angular, and jQuery;
- Styling UI components using MUI, UI Kit, Chakra UI, Kendo UI, Tailwind CSS, SCSS and Bootstrap;
- Testing with Jest, Karma, Jasmin and Cypress;
- SEO Optimization;
- REST API and GraphQL;
- WebPack and Babel for bundling web applications;

Back-end development

- Web application development with PHP frameworks and AWS;
- MySQL, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, and AWS DynamoDB;
- Unit testing with Jest and Jasmine;

Databases

- Experience in designing databases for distributed systems;
- Experience with optimizing long-running queries by MongoDB aggregations;
- Knowledge of scalability techniques for scaling databases;

DevOps

- Experience with Ubuntu and Windows operating systems;
- Experience in automation using provisioning tools like Jenkins;
- Experience with GitHub Actions;
- Experience with CI tools: AWS CodePipeline, Azure Pipelines and Gitlab;

Mobile development

- Experience with Java, and Android;
- Experience with tools: Android Studio, Eclipse;

Development methodologies

- Agile, Waterfall;
- Unit, integration and e2e testing;
- OOP, SOLID;
- Clean and team-oriented code

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Kaplan.Test.Prep North America(Full Remote)

Senior Frontend Engineer

Oct 2022 - Jul 2024

° Company Intranet - an internal web application of a education service company that helps business and task management of the company;

Main achievements and responsibilities:

- Led a team of 4 members to develop an internal website and related Windows applications with React.js, Next.js, MaterialUI, Laravel, PostgreSQL, and AI (FER);
- Excelled in server-side development for Education appplications using Java Spring Boot , MongoDB for creating robuts backend services and Google-auth for authentication and authorization.
- Designed and managed Relational (like MySQL, PostgreSQL) and NoSQL databases (like MongoDB), implementing robust data models and efficient queries for optimal performance.
- Implemented and managed cloud-based solutions on Amazon Web Service(AWS), optimizing infrastructure for performance and utilizing services such as Docker, Cloud Storage and Kubernetes Engine to enhance application scalability and reliability.
- Designed effective database table structures and optimized HTTP requests using the state management library Redux;
- Collaborated with the Scrum Master, the Product Owner, and Customers during development processes to confirm creative proposals and design best practices;
- Crafted well-defined GraphQL APIs using Apollo Client node module and implemented SOAP web services for seamless system integration and communication
- Reviewed the team members' code to improve the project's performance and reduce bugs.

<u>Used languages and technologies:</u> Java , JavaSpring Boot, React.js, Next.js, MaterialUI, Redux, CyPress, Jest, PHP, PostgreSQL, GraphQL, Git Bash

Magnolia Jewelers

Senior Software Engineer

Jun 2019 - Oct 2021

- Store Magnolia Website maintenance a festival advertising and management website that is aimed to organize and host a prestigious jewel advertisement that brings together artists, customers, and jewelers from around the world;
- Business Analytic and Management a groundbreaking connected product that offers over 200 flavor combinations, enhancing the culinary experience for both shop owners and their customers;

Main achievements and responsibilities:

- Was responsible for developing 3 websites using React.js, Angular, Next.js, Tailwind CSS, Laravel, CakePHP, MySQL, PostgreSQL, GraphQL and AWS;
- Exclusively used React-Hooks to handle application life-cycle processes
- Implemented CSS Box Model and styled web pages using CSS preprocessor SASS and effectively used mixins, functions, custom grid systems, grid-area concepts and flexbox for fluid-responsive application
- Built custom React.js components for UX-Library consisting Accordion, Filters, Dropdown, Carousel, Button, Checkbox, Input, Icons
- Applied Scrum principles to develop projects rapidly and satisfy customers;
- Worked as a Product owner to develop a festival website and successfully launched the project;
- Collaborated closely with project managers, and customers to launch the projects successfully and meet the deadline;
- Implemented the latest ECMAScript6 (ES6) features to enhance code standards and maintainability;
- Worked hard to implement sprint backlogs in a short period and guarantee excellent performance;
- Contributed to hands-on work on front-end and back-end development tasks;

<u>Used languages and technologies:</u> React.js, Redux, React WebSocket, Angular, NgRx, RxJs, Next.js, UI kit, Kendo UI, MUI, SASS, Tailwind CSS, Bootstrap, Karma, Jasmin, Laravel, CakePHP, MySQL, PostgreSQL, GraphQL, AWS

Scopic

Mid-Senior Software Engineer

May 2015 - Jun2019

Main achievements and responsibilities:

- Spearheaded the design and development of a high-performance, user-centric single music note
 detection web application, leveraging HTML5, Phaser, and the PitchFinder module. Achieved a
 significant 10% increase in customer engagement through efficient client-server communication and
 superior user experience.
- Used front-end testing libraries like Jest, Cypress, and Jasmine;
- Involved in a development team to develop the hotel reservation system by React.js, Node.js, MongoDB, and AWS services such as AWS lambda, API Gateway, S3 bucket, and Cognito;
- Designed, developed and tested HTML5, CSS3, Bootstrap, JavaScript, jQuery and React.js that meets
 accessibility and web browser standards for website;
- Built databases and table structures for web applications;
- Developed two Android system applications, such as Launcher and SystemUI;
- Utilized SOLID principles and algorithm concepts to improve the performance of microservices;
- Collaborated closely with team members to develop the project and learned many programming languages, such as HTML, CSS, JavaScript, TypeScript, C#, Python, Java, and SQL;
- Maintained proficiency in multiple programming languages;
- Participated in web scrapping website development using Angular and Python;
- Implemented React.js form validation using react-hook-form and yup library;

<u>Used languages and technologies:</u> Phaser , React.js, Redux, jQuery, Chakra UI, WebPack, Babel, Node.js, Jest, Cypress, Jasmine, HTTP caching system, Azure DevOps, Android, Python

ThoughtBot

Software Engineer

Sep 2012 - May 2015

Main achievements and responsibilities:

- Led the complete rewrite of the Atlas system using the CakePHP and EXTJS frameworks, resulting in significant performance improvements and enhanced user experience.
- Oversaw the continuous development and bi-weekly deployment cycles of Atlas, ensuring smooth updates and system stability.
- Designed and implemented a seamless interface for document scanning directly from TWAIN devices into the document archiving module, streamlining workflows.
- Introduced GIT version control across the development team, fostering more efficient collaboration and version tracking.
- Implemented a robust ticketing and bug-tracking system, optimizing the development workflow and enhancing issue resolution.
- Implemented the latest ECMAScript6 (ES6) features to enhance code standards and maintainability;
- Worked hard to implement sprint backlogs in a short period and guarantee excellent performance;

Delivered smaller Ruby on Rails-based web solutions, including http://lifecyclestudio.com, showcasing proficiency in rapid development of custom applications.

<u>Used languages and technologies:</u> React.js, Redux, React WebSocket, Angular, NgRx, RxJs, Next.js, UI kit, Kendo UI, MUI, SASS, Tailwind CSS, Bootstrap, Karma, Jasmin, Laravel, CakePHP, MySQL, PostgreSQL, GraphQL, AWS

Camper Creative

Junior Software Engineer

Jan 2010 - Jan 2012

Main achievements and responsibilities:

- Developed dynamic, data-driven websites and web applications using PHP 5 and MySQL, delivering robust solutions tailored to client needs.
- Applied advanced object-oriented programming principles to create modular and scalable software.
- Implemented MVC architecture and other design patterns to enhance the maintainability and scalability of web applications.
- Built complex, multi-tier web applications, ensuring seamless integration across various system layers.
- Embraced Agile development methodologies, particularly SCRUM, to drive efficient project execution and team collaboration.

<u>Used languages and technologies:</u> Phaser, React.js, Redux, jQuery, Chakra UI, WebPack, Babel, Node.js, Jest, Cypress, Jasmine, HTTP caching system, Azure DevOps, Android, Python

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Computer Science

University of Tennessee at Chattanooga